Lawrence A. Busha Papers VHP2004/17
CCSU Veterans History Project
Lawrence A. Busha Papers
Bulk, 1943-1946
1943-1946, 2004
VHP2004/17
CCSU Veterans History Project
133.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Busha, Lawrence A., 1922 -
Biographical/Historical note
Lawrence A. Busha enlisted in the U.S. Marine Corps on September 1, 1943. He chose the Marine Corps because of its reputation for "being the best", according to Busha. After basic training on Parris Island (SC), Busha went on to be a rifle instructor for incoming recruits at the camp. After 6 months of instructor duty, he was transferred to Camp Lejeune and Camp Pendleton for additional training. In April of 1945, he was shipped to Okinawa where he fought on the front lines in the "Battle of Okinawa", the bloodiest battle in Pacific during World War II. Busha describes in detail what the Marines endured on the front lines in Okinawa. After Okinawa, his platoon was sent to Guam to prepare for an invasion of Japan, however the bomb was dropped on Nagasaki before he was sent in. Busha finished out his time in the Marine Corps as part of a brig detachment in Tsingtao, China. He was sent home in the spring of 1946. On the train ride to Maryland, where he was to be discharged, his car derailed and killed or injured many of the marines aboard the train. He returned to New York for a time, but eventually moved to Connecticut where he worked at Bristol Brass for many years, becoming a member and leader in the United Auto Workers Union. He was later named Deputy Labor Commissioner in Connecticut because of his work with the union. He still keeps in touch with members of his squad through reunions and the division newsletter.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 4 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Publications
Series IV, Multi-media
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
United States. Marine Corps. A Company, 1st Battalion, 29th Marine Regiments.; United States. Marine Corps. Division, 6th.; Camp Lejeune (N.C.); Camp Pendleton (Calif.); Okinawa-shi (Japan); Parris Island (S.C.); Qingdao (China); San Diego (Calif.); World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Japan--Okinawa Island.
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - A memorial service held by the marines in Tsingtao, China for Sgt. Earl Ireton, who died in the troop train wreck in Marrisburg, PA., June 16, 1946; VHP2004/17.I.1; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Letter from Jack W. Houston to Busha telling that he was on the same train that derail in Harrisburn ,PA., November 2001; VHP2004/17.I.2; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Interview Sysnopsis, March 18, 2004; VHP2004/17.I.3
- Series II: Military Documents
  - Lawrence “Mike” Busha’s service records, 1943 - 1946; VHP2004/17.II.1; 6.0 Digital objects
  - Presidential Unit Citation to Sixth Marine Division, Reinforced, Circa May 1944 - September 1947; VHP2004/17.II.2
  - Lawrence “Mike” Busha’s certificate for his participation at the formal Japanese surrender ceremony, October 1945; VHP2004/17.II.3
  - Lawrence “Mike” Busha’s Honorable Discharge, May 29, 1946; VHP2004/17.II.4
- Series III: Publications
  - 1946 newspaper article about train wreck incident at Harrisburg, PA, May 1946; VHP2004/17.III.1
  - Picture of 1946 troops train wreck from newspaper, n.d.; VHP2004/17.III.2
  - Picture of 1946 troops train wreck incident from unknown newspaper show Lawrence Busha exiting the wrecked train, n.d.; VHP2004/17.III.3
  - History of the Sixth Marine Division book, 1987; VHP2004/17.III.4; 90.0 Digital objects
  - Page7 of 6th Marines Division News, Busha wrote to ask about the train wreck incident, Octomber - December 2001; VHP2004/17.III.5
  - Striking Sixth Newsletter - Fall/Winter 2005 issue, VHP2004/17.III.6; 8.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images
    - 22 years old Lawrence “Mike” Busha; Parris Island - Rifle Range, 1943; VHP2004/17.IV.1
    - Lawrence “Mike” Busha; Camp Lejeune, NC, 1944; VHP2004/17.IV.1
    - Lawrence “Mike” Busha; Camp Lejeune, NC, August 1944; VHP2004/17.IV.3
    - Unknown flame thrower; Hill 311, May 1945; VHP2004/17.IV.4
    - L - R: (rear) Hugh Larry, Selgret, Busha (front) Joe Bender, Art Sharkey - Guam, 1945; VHP2004/17.IV.4
    - L - R: Hugh Larry, Rick Leber, 1945; VHP2004/17.IV.6
    - 6th Brigade Detachment group photo in front of hotel (converted to U.S. barracks) - Tsingtao, China. Lawrence “Mike” Busha is in middle of back row., November 1945; VHP2004/17.IV.7
    - “JoJo”, Police Chief of Tsingtao (he was the Police Chief under the Japanese occupation) and Lawrence Busha; China, 1946; VHP2004/17.IV.8
    - 6th Brigade Detachment group photo; Busha is first person on right on back row - China, 1946; VHP2004/17.IV.9
    - Lawrence “Mike” Busha - China, 1946; VHP2004/17.IV.10
    - 6th Marines Division reunion; L - R: Leonard Marshall(TN), Lawrence Busha(CT), Bill Robertson(SC) - Cherry Hill, NJ, 1983; VHP2004/17.IV.11
    - Hugh F. Larry (USMC)’s WWII helmet, he had a close call on Okinawa on May 14, 1942., Photo taken 2004; VHP2004/17.IV.12
    - Hugh F. Larry, U.S. Marine Corps, 2004; VHP2004/17.IV.13
    - Lawrence “Mike” Busha, August 8, 2006; VHP2004/17.IV.14
  - Subseries B: Moving Images
    - Oral History Interview, March 18, 2004; VHP2004/17.IV.B.1; 1.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2004/17, Box VHP Interview 1)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      Interview video also available online.
      Streaming Video